またそんな顔して 唇噛み締めて
mata sonna kao wo shite
There you go, making that face again,
biting onto your lips.
kuchibiru kamishimete
弱さを隠してるけど
yowasa wo kakushiteru kedo
You're hiding your weak side,
sono hitomi no oku
but deep in those eyes,
その瞳の奥 うずくまる君が
uzukumaru kimi ga
I can see you cowering.
本当の心なら
honto no kokoro nara
If you had a true heart,
思って 泣いて 一人で 不安で
omotte, naite, hito yonde, fuwande
you would care, cry, call for someone and worry.
なんで 痛いの 持ってんだ
nande itai no mottenda
Why are you holding onto the pain?
僕に そっと 預けてよ
boku ni sotto azukete yo
Share some of it with me.
直ぐじゃ無理と思うのならば
sugu ja muri to omou no naraba
If you don't think it's possible right away,
少しずつでいい
sukoshi zutsu de ii
you can do it slowly, bit by bit.
翼の無い僕等はきっと
tsubasa no nai bokura kitto
We don't have wings,
tobenai toki mitsuketeru dake
but I'm sure we're only finding times that we can't fly.
飛べないと 決め付けてるだけ
koe no kagiri kimi wo yobu yo
I'll call for you to the limits of my voice
声の限り君を呼ぶよ 迷わないように
mayowanai you ni
so that you won't get lost.
フワリ心舞い上がれ あの風に乗せて
fuwari kokoro maiagare
Soar up to the sky with your gentle heart,
ano kaze ni nosete issei erose
ride on that wind, and get it all at once.
Natsume
Yuujinchou
こんにちは
Hello.
ひょっとして蛍を見に来たの
Did you come by to see the fireflies?
はい そろそろ季節だって聞いて
Yes.
I heard that it was almost the season for them.
そうか
I see.
It seems you were a bit too early, time and season-wise.
でも 時間的にも時期的にもちょっと早かったみたいだね
数も減っているらしいし
Their numbers have dropped too.
そうですか
Is that so?
Well then, excuse me.
それじゃ 失礼します
あいつ あの人に憑いているのかな
I wonder if she possessed him.
そのようだな
Seems so.
You...
お前 人の子のくせに見えるのか
You can see me even though you're a human child?
Geez...
やれやれ 危なっかしい人の子だ
What a careless human child.
Fleeting Light
Is this okay with you?
いいのか 俺なんかに構ってて
Bothering with me, I mean.
さっきの人に取り憑いてたんじゃないのか
Weren't you possessing that person from before?
Possessing?
取り憑く 失礼な
How rude.
He's my friend.
あれは私の友人だ
Friend?
友人
So he can see Youkai?
じゃあ あの人 妖怪が見えるのか
It's an old story.
昔の話だ
若い頃のあの人とはよく話をした
I used to talk a lot to him when he was young.
しばらくはずっと一緒にいた
For a while, we were always together.
でも ある日突然 あの人は私のことが見えなくなった
But one day, he suddenly couldn't see me anymore.
And that's it.
それっきりだ
He couldn't see you anymore?
見えなくなったって そんなことあるのか
Can that even happen?
大人になると そういう力が衰えるものもいるらしい
When people become adults, those kinds of powers tend to become weaker.
I see.
あ そうか そんなこともあるのか
So that happens too...
I heard that he would be getting married soon,
私はあの人が近々結婚すると聞いたので
せめて晴姿を見るだけでもと思ってきたのさ
so I thought I would at least see his big day.
まあ 私たちはちょうど お前達のような関係だったんだ
Well, our relationship was a lot like yours.
うん 私らは友人関係ではない
We're not friends!
飼い主とペットの関係だ
Our relationship is that of a master and pet!
うっ そうか
I see.
What's your name?
お前 名前は
当ててみろ
Try guessing.
Mask.
お面
Blond hair.
長髪
I got it! It's pond woman!
分かった 沼女だ
私は下等な妖だ そもそも名前はない
I'm a low-level Ayakashi.
Plus, I didn't have a name in the first place.
Don't tease me.
からかうなよ
I'll give you a name, then!
なら私が名を付けてやろう
What about Curly-noodles?
縮れ面でどうだ
What do you think?
どうだ どうだどうだ
Come on, what do you think?
また人の子と話せるとはな
I didn't think I'd be able to talk to another person.
おい ちぢれ ちぢれ麺 おい
This must be fate.
これも何かの縁だ
式の日まで世話になるぞ
I'll be in your care until the ceremony.
I said, what do you think?!
どうだと言っておろうが ちぢれ面でどうだ
What do you think about Curly-noodles?!
うるさいぞ ニャンコ先生
Shut up, Nyanko-sensei!
なく なあ ちぢれ
Then how about Curly?
What a dull radiance.
地味に眩しい
おーい もう寝てしまうのか
Hey.
You're going to sleep already?
You're so boring.
つまらんぞ
おい 聞いてるのか
Hey, are you listening?
おい 起きろってば
Hey, wake up.
Hey!
おい
その夜 誰かが呼んでいる夢を見た
That night, I had a dream where someone was calling out.
Kiyo...
キヨ キヨ
Takashi-kun.
貴志君 遅刻するわよ
You're going to be late!
Wake up, I have to go out.
起きてくれ 出かけなきゃ
How about "Kiyo"?
キヨってのはどうだ
How about "Kiyo" as your name?
名前 キヨってことにしないか
好きにしろ
Do what you want.
妖怪が見えなくなる
Becoming unable to see Youkai...
そんなこともあるのか
So that can happen too?
A long time ago, there was a mountain god in this forest
昔この森に住む山神の一人が
人間の女と恋をして夜中にこっそり逢瀬を重ねていた
that fell in love with a human woman, and they would rendezvous secretly at night.
その時 深い闇の中
During those times, the fireflies from this pond would light the way for them in the pitch-black darkness.
この沼の蛍達が夜道を照らしてやったのだ
To thank them, the mountain god turned the short-lived fireflies into Ayakashi.
山神はその礼に 命短い蛍達を妖の姿に変えてやった
彼らは喜んで その多くが沼を旅立って行ってしまった
In their joy, many of them left the pond,
ここの蛍はその時この地に残ったものの子孫だと言われている
and the fireflies here are said to be the descendants of those who stayed behind.
まあ ただの言い伝えだがな
Well, it's just a legend, though.
へえ
Look!
見ろ
こここら
H-H-Hey!
Watch out!
危ない
いったたたた
You're...
キミは 昨日の
the one from yesterday.
S-Sorry, I think I tripped over something.
す すいません なんかに躓いちゃったみたいで
元気だね
You're a feisty one.
あのう
Excuse me...
Is there something in this pond?
この沼 何かいますか
Something?
何か
Yeah.
はい
さあ 蛍のほかには鮒くらいかな
Not sure. Besides the fireflies, I guess there are carp.
あの妖は人は襲わんのだ
That Ayakashi doesn't attack people.
そうか
I see.
聞けない あなたも妖怪が見えたんですか なんて
I couldn't ask him.
I couldn't ask him if he could see Youkai too.
Going to see a human who could see them,
見える人間が会いに行って
and asking them about their past would just be trouble for them.
今更昔の話を蒸し返されても迷惑なだけだろう
キヨ
Kiyo...
あの人は彰文さんって言うんだ
That person is called Akifumi-san.
あの人は妖が見えることで
Because he could see Ayakashi,
家族からも周りからも 変な目で見られて苦しんでいた
he suffered much from the looks he got from his family and others.
ここへ一人で泣きにくるのを そっと隠れていつも見ていた
He would come here to cry by himself,
and I would hide quietly and watch him.
でもある日 夜中にやってきて
But one day, he came during the night.
私は慌てて隠れたけれど 体が光ってしまって
In a rush, I tried to hide,
but something caught onto my body.
Who's there?!
そこにいるのはだれだ
妖怪か
A Youkai?
あ 待って
Wait!
待って
いたっ
Could we talk for a bit?
少し話さないか 私は その
I, ah...
I'm interested in humans.
人間に興味があるんだ
俺は 妖怪なんかに興味はない
I'm not interested in Youkai, though.
でも 次の日も彼はきてくれた
But...
He came the next day too.
We talked about many things.
私たちはいろいろ話した
We talked and talked so much.
いっぱい いっぱい話をして
時々 一緒に遊びに行って
Sometimes, we would play together.
こんな手触りなのか
So this is how it feels?
気持ちいい
It feels nice.
本当だ
You're right...
You're right.
でも ある日
But on one day, his eyes could no longer see me.
あの人の目は私を映さなくなった
私が触れても気付かなくなった
He wouldn't notice even if I touched him.
あの人は沼に来て 何度も呼んだけど
He would come to the pond and I would call for him several times,
yet he couldn't see me even when I stood right in front of him.
目の前に立つ私が見えなかった
お前も いつの日か 見えなくなるだろうか
I wonder if you'll be unable to see us one day?
That would be terrible.
いやだな
What am I saying?
何言ってるんだ
Wasn't that my wish for the longest time?
それが長い間の 俺の望みだったじゃないか
I had always, always wished to be free from all this.
ずっと ずっと 解放されるときを 望んでいたはずじゃ
I thought I wanted to know.
知りたいと思った
淡く光るキヨの姿が もう見えないのに
He can no longer see Kiyo's fleeting light,
so why does he continue to go to the pond?
なぜ あの沼へ行くのか
I see, so you can see Ayakashi too.
そうか キミも妖が見えるのか
Yes.
はい
A Youkai I met recently told me you could once see them.
最近出会った妖怪に 以前あなたも見えていたと教えられて
When I think about it, it was all like a dream.
今となっては 何もかも夢のようだ
Is it tough?
辛いかい
It was tough on me because I was always alone.
僕は辛かったよ
いつも一人だったから
でも 一人の妖と仲良くなってね
But I was able to get along well with one Ayakashi.
I came to like her.
好きになった
I couldn't say it,
言えなかったけど 愛していたんだ
but I loved her.
それが ある日突然 妖のことが全く見えなくなってしまって
But one day, I suddenly couldn't see Ayakashi anymore.
And that was it.
それきりだった
I just couldn't forget about her, so I didn't get married.
どうしてもあの子のことが忘れられなくて結婚もせずにいたんだけど
やっと やっと心から 愛する女性に会うことができたんだ
But...
But I finally met a girl I could love with all my heart.
And she's a very nice person, too.
とても心の優しい人にね
Our wedding ceremony will be held in three days.
三日後に式を挙げるんだ
I won't come here anymore, then.
そしたらもう ここへはこない
Akifumi-san!
彰文さん
行かなくちゃ
I have to go now.
それじゃ またね
See you again.
Okay.
はい
Thank goodness.
よかった
Kiyo.
キヨ
He found someone important to him.
大切な人を見つけたんだな
あの人はもう一人ではないんだな
He's...
not alone anymore.
Kiyo...
キヨ キミはそれでいいのかい
Is that okay with you?
On that night,
その夜静かな夢を見た
I had a peaceful dream.
それは多分 キヨから流れてくる記憶
It was probably Kiyo's memory that flowed into me.
Hotaru!
蛍 お~い
Hey!
Hotaru!
蛍 どこにいるんだ
Where are you?!
Hotaru!
蛍 見えない 出てきてくれ
I can't see you! Please come out!
Hotaru!
蛍  俺の傍に
Don't leave...
Hotaru...
蛍
Please come out...
出てきてくれ
Do you hate me now?
俺のこと嫌いになったのかい
I love you.
好き 好きよ
Love you...
I love you.
好きよ 好き
I love you...
I love you!
好きよ
I'm...
俺は彰文さんじゃないよ
not Akifumi-san.
Hotaru.
蛍
That's what you were called, right?
キミはそう呼ばれていたんだね
I saw and heard it.
見えた 聞こえたよ
I am a firefly Ayakashi.
私は蛍の妖
実体を持たないが
I won't be able to keep it,
一度だけ ただの虫の姿に戻ることができる
but I'm able to return to being a simple bug just once.
Then you won't be able to keep your current form,
そうなると 今の姿には戻れず
and your life will end as a bug.
虫としての寿命で命が終わると聞いたことがある
Or so I've heard.
Even so, I don't mind.
それでも構わない
Even without me...
私がいなくても
もう あの人は笑ってくれる
He will continue to laugh.
Then, at the very least,
ならばせめてもう一度
even as a bug,
虫の姿でもいい
I want to see him.
あの人に会いたい
Wait, Hotaru!
蛍 待って
あ 待っ
Wai-!
I hope she's not intending to head towards the pond.
あいつ 沼へ行くつもりじゃあるまいな
That huge, big-mouthed guy doesn't attack humans,
沼にいたあの口のでかい奴は人は襲わないが蛍を食うのだ
but he eats fireflies.
Because he's going around and eating them,
奴が食べて回っているからここらの蛍はどこかに隠れてしまっておるんだ
all the fireflies here are hiding somewhere.
Where are you, Hotaru?!
蛍 どこだ
What are you doing?
何をしとる
It's too dark.
暗くて
How irritating.
ちっ 焦れったい
Get on!
乗れ
あ いた
There she is!
止めろ
Stop!
Where's Hotaru?
蛍は
She ran away after that.
今ので逃げたか
この匂い 別の奴だ
This smell... it's someone else's!
それじゃ
Then...
My mom got really mad then.
あの時 お袋 すごく驚いててさ
Right?
ねえ
It's pretty, huh?
きれいね
本当だ きれいだな
Yeah.
It's really pretty.
It's like...
まるで
あ 待って
Wait!
Sensei...
先生 沼の蛍達が見守った山神様と恋人は
Did everything go well for the mountain god and his lover that the fireflies protected?
うまく行ったのかな
Who knows.
さあな 妖と違って人の命は短いからな
Unlike Ayakashi, humans have a short lifespan.
Hotaru.
蛍 僕もいつかは 失う日が来るのだろうか
Will the day come when I can't see them either?
These one-sided encounters and these troubling days...
一方的に訪れる出会いを 煩わしい日々を
Will it be liberating for me?
それは僕にとって 解放だろうか
Or...
それとも
At that time,
その時 小さな蛍が 何かを囁いた気がした
I felt that the small firefly whispered something to me.
けれど 虫の言葉は 僕には分からなかった
However,
I couldn't understand the bug's words.
さよなら 蛍
Goodbye, Hotaru.
I wonder if he understood them?
あの人には分かるだろうか
Maybe only he could...
あの人にだけは
おめでとう
お幸せに
先輩おめでとうございます
お幸せにね
It's tough when you can't do anything, even though you can see them.
見えるのに 何もしてやれないっていうのは 辛いな
You're an idiot.
お前は阿呆なんだ
You don't have any obligation to help out everyone.
いちいちしてやる義理などなかろうが
In the end, Youkai and humans are completely different.
妖怪と人間は所詮別物だ
But...
でも
言っとくがな 夏目
Let me tell you this, Natsume.
お前が見えなくなったとしても
Even if you couldn't see us anymore, I wouldn't let you get away until you give me the Book of Friends.
友人帳を頂くまでは逃がさんからな
たとえいつの日か 妖怪が目の前から姿を消しても
Even if the Youkai before me disappear one day,
出会った思い出は 決して消えることはないだろう
the memories from my encounters with them will never disappear.
Then how about you make an effort to be my bodyguard?
だったら 俺の用心棒に励んでくれよ
You promised, right, sensei?
約束だろ 先生
And they will never go away.
それは決して 何一つ
Not a single one.
色づく 西空に
hi no tsukurishi zora ni
On that day where the sky was ablaze,
差し込む一筋の陽
sashikomu hitosuji no hi
and rays of light were piercing through,
yuudachi no ameagari ni
the evening rain had stopped,
夕立の雨上がりに
気付く夏の匂い
kizuku natsu no nioi
I noticed the scent of summer,
ひしめく光が照らす
hishimeku hikari ga terasu
and the crowded, shining lights.
想いに耳を澄ませば
omoi ni mimi wo sumaseba
If I turned my ear to my thoughts,
聴こえし友の面影
kikoeshi tomo no omokage
I could hear traces of my dear friends.
夏夕空 薫り立つ
natsu yuuzora kawarirazu
The summer evening sky
鮮やかな過ぎ去りし日々
azayaka na sugisarishi hibi
and the vivid passing days were just the same,
心のまま笑いあった
kokoro no mama warai atta
and so I laughed; it was just like
あの夏の思い出よ
ano natsu no omoide yo
my memory of that summer.
Next Time on
Natsume Yuujinchou
Ayakashi Exorcism
Who are you?
あなたは
俺は名取周一
I'm Natori Shuuichi.
Could you help me out with an exorcism job, Natsume-kun?
夏目君 お祓いの仕事を手伝ってくれないか
An exorcism?
お祓い？
There seems to be some kind of aura coming from you.
っていうか お前何やら新手の妖気が出ておるぞ
Sorry for being so fabulous.
きらめいてて ゴメン
His aura...
妖気だ